<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.7"
          urlbase="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/"
          
          maintainer="webmaster@eclipse.org"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>346046</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-05-17 04:11:00 -0400</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>[api] provide an extension point for registering URL handlers (was: Hyperlinks to builds should open in task editor)</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2012-05-01 03:14:13 -0400</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>14</classification_id>
          <classification>Mylyn</classification>
          <product>Mylyn Commons</product>
          <component>UI</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard></status_whiteboard>
          <keywords>noteworthy, plan</keywords>
          <priority>P2</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>3.7</target_milestone>
          <dependson>357738</dependson>
    
    <dependson>370186</dependson>
    
    <dependson>370504</dependson>
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Sascha Scholz">sascha.scholz</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</assigned_to>
          <cc>googleclone</cc>
    
    <cc>mik.kersten</cc>
    
    <cc>shawn.minto</cc>
    
    <cc>steffen.pingel</cc>
          
          <votes>0</votes>

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>1931462</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Sascha Scholz">sascha.scholz</who>
    <bug_when>2011-05-17 04:11:11 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Hudson/Jenkins is often used to verify changes in the Gerrit code review system. After a change has been proposed, Hudson fetches  the change, builds it, puts a voting in the &apos;Verified&apos; category and adds a comment pointing to the build (as an example see http://egit.eclipse.org/r/#change,3441).

There is also a Mylyn Connector for Gerrit available in the Mylyn Reviews project which is able to show all the data (including the comments) in a task editor. Currently, if you click on a link to the build it&apos;s opened in a web browser. It would be nice if the link could be opened in a task editor for the build (if a Hudson for this URL is  registered).

Is it possible to register a general-purpose handler for RLs pointing to Hudson builds which provides this behavior?</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>1932365</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2011-05-17 18:26:27 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>That&apos;s an excellent idea that we should definitely consider for the next release to facilitate linking between the different artifacts. I am not sure where this would go but my first guess is that this is a platform concern and should be provided in the commons on the bottom of the stack.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>1944295</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Frank Becker">eclipse</who>
    <bug_when>2011-06-04 14:39:02 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Sascha,
Steffen,

we have multiple Hyperlinks for Attachments in the Bugzilla Editor. Maybe we can use this to!</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>1974044</commentid>
    <comment_count>3</comment_count>
    <who name="Torkild Resheim">torkildr</who>
    <bug_when>2011-08-04 04:09:45 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>There is a similar issue with regards to the Hudson/Jenkins discovery notification and the notifications framework. Handlers are implemented in the ServiceMessageControl. As a result the builds view can handle links properly but the notification popup can not. It would be great to have a common mechanism.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>1976018</commentid>
    <comment_count>4</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2011-08-09 08:47:56 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>(In reply to comment #3)
&gt; There is a similar issue with regards to the Hudson/Jenkins discovery
&gt; notification and the notifications framework. Handlers are implemented in the
&gt; ServiceMessageControl. As a result the builds view can handle links properly but
&gt; the notification popup can not. It would be great to have a common mechanism.

I believe that the notification popup uses a Label whereas the service message uses a Link control which can cause inconsistencies. I agree that we should have common renderer and handling mechanism for this.  Please file a separate bug against Commons/Notifications to track that since it&apos;s not directly related to this bug.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2058423</commentid>
    <comment_count>5</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-01-31 01:53:44 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>I have pushed a proposal to http://review.mylyn.org/231. Shawn, it&apos;d be great if you could take a look and let me know what you think.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2058948</commentid>
    <comment_count>6</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-01-31 16:44:42 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>I have pushed the changes to master. Leaving open as a reminder to document the change.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2059328</commentid>
    <comment_count>7</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-02-01 11:04:09 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>URL handlers can be registered through the org.eclipse.mylyn.commons.workbench.urlHandlers extension point. Implementors need to extend AbstractUrlHandler which gets passed a location and returns a boolean whether the URL was handled or not. The first handler to return true wins. The invocation order is controlled through a priority that can be specified in the handler. Handlers with higher priorties are invoked first.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2061058</commentid>
    <comment_count>8</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-02-04 13:33:06 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>I have added a org.eclipse.mylyn.commons.workbench.browser.UrlHyperlink class which implements IHyperlink and uses BrowserUtil.openUrl() to open hyperlinks in rich editors when available.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2100909</commentid>
    <comment_count>9</comment_count>
    <who name="Robert Pattinson">googleclone</who>
    <bug_when>2012-05-01 03:14:13 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Spam removed by droy 2012-05-01</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>