<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.7"
          urlbase="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/"
          
          maintainer="webmaster@eclipse.org"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>363838</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-11-15 10:39:00 -0500</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>create new user via ldap resolution shall be case insensitive</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2012-01-24 15:35:26 -0500</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>14</classification_id>
          <classification>Mylyn</classification>
          <product>Mylyn Reviews R4E</product>
          <component>UI</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Windows Vista</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard></status_whiteboard>
          <keywords></keywords>
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>normal</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>0.9</target_milestone>
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Alvaro Sanchez-Leon">alvsan09</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</assigned_to>
          <cc>lmcbout</cc>
          
          <votes>0</votes>

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2026713</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Alvaro Sanchez-Leon">alvsan09</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-15 10:39:49 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>When creating a new review participant, entering the userid and pressing enter resolves is automatically via LDAP (if configured).
  However the userid is found as long as the case sensitivity entered matches the entry in the LDAP data base.
  However if the Find button is used the actual Find Dialogue accepts a userid and the search is not case sensitive.
  
  The behaviour should be consistent so entering the id in the new participant dialog should not be case sensitive.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2026820</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-15 13:05:45 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>Fix is implemented.  We anre now case-insensitive for Participants (in dialog) and User (in preferences)</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2027890</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Jacques Bouthillier">lmcbout</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-17 09:05:41 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>After testing on LINUX, I am able to add a participant with UPPER case letter. Also, if I enter a participant and press enter, the e-mail does not get adjusted if LDAP is available and I can have a mixed of upper and lower case character.

I also tested on WINDOW VISTA environment. Here, it seems the event for the &quot;ENTER&quot; button is performed after the &quot;LOSE focus&quot; event is done, so the data for the participant is updated in lower case as well as the e-mail information.

When I press &quot;ENTER&quot; in the participant field ID, the dialogue should not close and the field should be validated only.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2028034</commentid>
    <comment_count>3</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-17 11:54:13 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>Fixed Jacques issues and updated code as per Alvaro&apos;s comments</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2028328</commentid>
    <comment_count>4</comment_count>
    <who name="Alvaro Sanchez-Leon">alvsan09</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-17 23:36:30 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>* The R4E preference page - User tab, changed the UserID label to &quot;Name:&quot; (Linux)
* Unable to resolve user ids populated in capital letters in LDAP from the enter participant details dialog, 
   however it&apos;s possible to do it from the preferences pages and the find user dialog.
* using a work space populated with R4E preferences user id in capitals does not get updated to lower case when installing the new version
     even if the review navigator is closed and re-opened it takes no effect. Capital letters remain.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2028759</commentid>
    <comment_count>5</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2011-11-18 13:52:17 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>Ok sorry about that.  Everything should be OK now.</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>