<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.7"
          urlbase="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/"
          
          maintainer="webmaster@eclipse.org"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>374458</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2012-03-16 02:31:00 -0400</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>open attachments with system editor</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-11-04 13:35:19 -0500</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>14</classification_id>
          <classification>Mylyn</classification>
          <product>Mylyn Tasks</product>
          <component>Framework</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Windows 7</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard>sprint=7;effort=1;</status_whiteboard>
          <keywords>noteworthy, plan</keywords>
          <priority>P2</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>3.10</target_milestone>
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Mik Kersten">mik.kersten</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</assigned_to>
          <cc>leo.dos.santos</cc>
    
    <cc>sam.davis</cc>
    
    <cc>shawn.minto</cc>
    
    <cc>steffen.pingel</cc>
          
          <votes>0</votes>

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2081601</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Mik Kersten">mik.kersten</who>
    <bug_when>2012-03-16 02:31:25 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Currently the Attachments table appears to always open with the web browser, which yields undesirable behavior on Windows in pretty much all cases (not sure about Linux or Mac).  Could we defautl the opening to be the system editor, on Windows at least?</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2085335</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-03-23 19:16:12 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Doesn&apos;t the attachment table persist the choice and opens future files of the same type in the selected editor? I&apos;m not sure that we would want to change it since browsers can handle many file types and offer more advanced streaming than the mechanism that is used when opening files in system editors.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2085714</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Mik Kersten">mik.kersten</who>
    <bug_when>2012-03-26 08:59:34 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I am not sure what the behavior is on Linux or Mac.  But on Windows the behavior of opening the file with the browser is almost always less desirable than opening with the system editor.  What&apos;s even worse, is that for repositories that require authentication, opening the attachment with the browser requires the user to enter their credentials, breaking the flow, whereas opening with the system editor does not.  

I think it&apos;s fine for this behavior to be OS dependent, eg, if on Linux it&apos;s better to keep the browser as default.  But what I&apos;m trying to point out here is that for Windows I think it&apos;s pretty clear that we have the wrong default.  This is compounded by the fact it&apos;s hard for non-advanced users to discover the &quot;Open with&quot;, and the fact that &quot;Open with&quot; only remembers it&apos;s preference per file type.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2086349</commentid>
    <comment_count>3</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2012-03-27 14:05:15 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I agree strongly with Mik that this is the wrong default, at least for Windows. I suspect it may be wrong for Linux too. I think it creates a significantly bad experience for new users, and I&apos;ve been meaning to create a bug for it for a long time.

(In reply to comment #1)
&gt; Doesn&apos;t the attachment table persist the choice and opens future files of the
&gt; same type in the selected editor? 

Based on how often I need to specify which editor to use, I feel like it either forgets my choice after some time, or has some more complex way of choosing it than a per-file-type rule.

&gt; I&apos;m not sure that we would want to change it
&gt; since browsers can handle many file types 

The way that browsers (at least Firefox and Internet Explorer) handle most file types, e.g. images, is to pop up a dialog asking if you want to save it or open it in the system editor.

&gt; and offer more advanced streaming than
&gt; the mechanism that is used when opening files in system editors.

I think it is a defect that downloading attachments happens with a modal progress dialog (see also bug 342077).</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2086394</commentid>
    <comment_count>4</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2012-03-27 15:11:02 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Thanks for the input. I have put this on the backlog.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2185366</commentid>
    <comment_count>5</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2012-11-19 18:53:19 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>I&apos;ve created the following review:

8775: 342077: attachments should be downloaded in the background from the task editor [I3ff81534]
https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/c/8775/

I realized that for text files, the best default is to use the default workbench editor, so I decided to use that when there is no preference set, and use the system editor only when there is no preference set and no default workbench editor. This means that in a clean Eclipse on Windows, text files are opened in the internal text editor, and images are opened in the system editor.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2253032</commentid>
    <comment_count>6</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-06 17:51:54 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>The proposed change looks good. I&apos;m wondering if we should add a warning dialog similar to how browsers do this before opening files that &quot;can harm your computer&quot;?</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2253043</commentid>
    <comment_count>7</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-06 18:29:50 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>That could make sense. If we do, it should have a checkbox to not show it again.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2253046</commentid>
    <comment_count>8</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-06 18:36:32 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>(In reply to comment #7)
&gt; That could make sense. If we do, it should have a checkbox to not show it again.

Can you add that to your change? I don&apos;t want to make the system editor the default unless we have some level of warning in place.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2253054</commentid>
    <comment_count>9</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-06 18:53:55 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Ok, but I&apos;m unsure when I will have time to do that.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2253126</commentid>
    <comment_count>10</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-07 03:26:57 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Ok, I&apos;ll take this of the milestone for now but we can reconsider in case we get to it in the next couple of days.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2258994</commentid>
    <comment_count>11</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-17 16:43:53 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I&apos;ve updated the review so that we will display a dialog with &quot;Some files can harm your computer when opened. Are you sure you want to open {0}?&quot; when any file is opened in the system editor. This will always be displayed until the user disables the warning. How is that?</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2298161</commentid>
    <comment_count>12</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-08-22 18:57:22 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I have merged the change.</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>