<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.7"
          urlbase="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/"
          
          maintainer="webmaster@eclipse.org"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>402082</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2013-02-28 23:16:00 -0500</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>open build editor immediately and populate when data is available</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-11-04 13:30:15 -0500</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>14</classification_id>
          <classification>Mylyn</classification>
          <product>Mylyn Builds</product>
          <component>Framework</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Windows 7</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard>effort=2;</status_whiteboard>
          <keywords>contributed, noteworthy</keywords>
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>1.2</target_milestone>
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</assigned_to>
          <cc>steffen.pingel</cc>
    
    <cc>tomasz.zarna</cc>
          
          <votes>0</votes>

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2224282</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-02-28 23:16:19 -0500</bug_when>
    <thetext>Similarly to links to attachments on Bugzilla tasks, when the user hovers over a link to a build, there should be a popup with the option to open the build in the browser. The reason is that in many cases, e.g. when there are subjobs, all of the important information is only accessible through the web ui. Having to wait for the build editor to open to click the open in browser button hampers the user experience.

I guess it could make sense to provide this option for a link to any task as well, but the task editor is sufficiently full-featured that it shouldn&apos;t be needed.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2238669</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-02 10:24:01 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>This sound reasonable to me. Alternatively the build editor could be changed to open immediately with a progress indicator embedded in the editor if build information is not cached locally.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2238863</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-02 14:44:51 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>That sounds like a good idea. I think I would actually want both.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2300897</commentid>
    <comment_count>3</comment_count>
    <who name="Tomasz Zarna">tomasz.zarna</who>
    <bug_when>2013-08-29 15:32:10 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>After looking around a bit, I thought it going to be trivial to fix by simply improving how AbstractRepositoryConnectorUi.findHyperlinks(TaskRepository, ITask, String, int, int) is implemented for Build connectors. The thing is that BuildConnectorUi is not a subclass of AbstractRepositoryConnectorUi, so technically it&apos;s not a connector. Moreover, the bundle introduces it&apos;s own connector extension point.

I guess this is all for a reason, and changing that sounds like an overkill. So I thought that maybe a better approach here would be addressing TODO from AbstractRepositoryConnectorUi javadoc: _Extend to provide connector-specific UI extensions. TODO: consider refactoring into extension points_ , defining an extension point for detecting hyperlinks and adding such extension in the Hudson &quot;connector&quot;. That of course would be backward compatible making the link detector from Mylyn Task use both links produced by connectors and extensions.

Does the above sound like worth trying or is there a different path I could take?</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2300964</commentid>
    <comment_count>4</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-08-29 16:42:40 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>(In reply to comment #3)
&gt; Does the above sound like worth trying or is there a different path I could
&gt; take?

I&apos;m wondering if we should extend the existing hyperlink extension point to always offer to open URLs in the browser in addition to a rich editor. I haven&apos;t looked at where that is happening but I would hope that we can handle it in the framework rather than requiring changes to connectors.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2314091</commentid>
    <comment_count>5</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-03 17:38:57 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>We won&apos;t have time to that for 3.10 but I&apos;d like to do what Steffen suggested in comment 1 if we can. This is very rough but works:

17013: 402082: [WIP] open build editor immediately and populate when data is available [Ic87178dd]
https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/c/17013/

The only thing I see that doesn&apos;t work is that there is a small layout bug where the controls don&apos;t always grab horizontal space when the editor is populated. There is no progress bar in the editor but maybe having it in the status area is enough.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2314574</commentid>
    <comment_count>6</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-04 16:28:21 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I was able to fix the layout issue just by calling layout().</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2316343</commentid>
    <comment_count>7</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-09 12:57:32 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>The latest revision on the review looks good. I&apos;m wondering though if it is better to display the progress message in the content area of the editor. It confused me that the title which display the build or task id in other contexts was changing and used to display an error.  I have also seen other editors behave that way showing a &quot;Loading....&quot; label in the content area initially.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2316384</commentid>
    <comment_count>8</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-09 14:46:48 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>To me it would make more sense to have a message area like the task editor does but I don&apos;t have time to add that. This is the closest thing to it. Maybe we could do what you suggest instead but I don&apos;t know how to make a label in a huge white space look good.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2316463</commentid>
    <comment_count>9</comment_count>
    <who name="Steffen Pingel">steffen.pingel</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-09 18:07:30 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>I merged the change. Thanks! Should we close this or do we want to keep it open since the committed change doesn&apos;t quite follow the original request.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2316468</commentid>
    <comment_count>10</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-10-09 18:43:52 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Thanks. Let&apos;s close this. We can open another bug for the other idea if we decide we want it, too.</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>