<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/page.cgi?id=bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="4.4.7"
          urlbase="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/"
          
          maintainer="webmaster@eclipse.org"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>406028</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2013-04-18 15:42:00 -0400</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>every time I try to open a file in a patch set, I am prompted to clone the repository</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-05-10 19:56:49 -0400</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>14</classification_id>
          <classification>Mylyn</classification>
          <product>Mylyn Reviews</product>
          <component>Gerrit Connector</component>
          <version>unspecified</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Windows 7</op_sys>
          <bug_status>RESOLVED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc></bug_file_loc>
          <status_whiteboard></status_whiteboard>
          <keywords></keywords>
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>normal</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.0</target_milestone>
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</assigned_to>
          <cc>sebastien.dubois</cc>
    
    <cc>shawn.minto</cc>
          
          <votes>0</votes>

      

      

      

          <comment_sort_order>oldest_to_newest</comment_sort_order>  
          <long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2245646</commentid>
    <comment_count>0</comment_count>
    <who name="Sam Davis">sam.davis</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-18 15:42:40 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Every time I try to open a file in a patch set, I am prompted to clone the repository.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2245649</commentid>
    <comment_count>1</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-18 15:46:40 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>This is a side effect of my solution for bug 400266. Normally this only happens if the repository that holds the file under review is not in the workspace.  Can you confirm that this is the case.  I can disable the dialog and open the file from the review spce silently, but then you will lose the code navigability functionality that the solution to bug 400266 introduces.</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2245724</commentid>
    <comment_count>2</comment_count>
    <who name="Miles Parker">milesparker</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-18 17:50:23 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>(In reply to comment #1)
&gt; Normally this only happens
&gt; if the repository that holds the file under review is not in the workspace.  Can
&gt; you confirm that this is the case. 

This is what I get.

&gt; I can disable the dialog and open the file
&gt; from the review spce silently, but then you will lose the code navigability
&gt; functionality that the solution to bug 400266 introduces.

I think that is better. We should just deal the best we can with whatever the user has in their workspace. We could try to find a less intrusive way to inform the user*, but in any case we should do away with this for now.

*One idea is to have an exclamation mark icon or something in the compare editor (icons are themselves problematic) saying, &quot;this file is not available locally. Click to retrieve the repository.&quot;</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2249079</commentid>
    <comment_count>3</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2013-04-26 11:58:31 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>For now, I only disabled showing the cloning dialog when opening files that cannot be resolved to a local Git repository.  The file name in the compare editor is still enclosed in brackets [], as per bug 400266, to show that the file is not in any local repo and that Eclipse code navigation will not be possible.  Ideally, we should show a decorator in the Gerrit Task editor / Review Navigator to make this fact more obvious to the user.  This should be tackled as part of the solution for bug 405978</thetext>
  </long_desc><long_desc isprivate="0" >
    <commentid>2255300</commentid>
    <comment_count>4</comment_count>
    <who name="Sebastien Dubois">sebastien.dubois</who>
    <bug_when>2013-05-10 16:19:39 -0400</bug_when>
    <thetext>Fix is now merged in</thetext>
  </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>